Guide to the Herbert F. Janick Jr. Papers MS 012
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series 3: Subject Files, 38885
  - Oral Histories - Student Work - Introduction to Historical Research, 38894
    - Western Connecticut State University -- History., 38895
      - Dr. Bruce King (interview) Creator: King, Dr. Bruce Interviewer(s): Sean Larkin and Faye Leone Interview location: White Hall Running time: 47 min., May 11, 1998; 38932; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 38)
        Topics discussed: (side A): Time at WestConn; 1978; 1997; Basic Studies program here when he came; worked part; time in that program; Taught about 20 years before coming to WestConn; Started Math Clinic; intended to be used by basic studies students; most who came weren't the ones who really needed it though; some from advanced courses came primarily; took it over after 1986 after sabbatical; Taught basic level and grad level courses; Geometry; Bob Hoburg and Jim Oliver; chairmen of Math department when he was there; Computer Science; hard to hire teachers for it during 1980s; taught some lower level courses; Student changes; no significant changes; Westside campus; came before it opened (opened early 1980s); decisions on who would move there; Business school was always going to move there; math department had opportunity to move there, but didn't; math department would have been able to have better offices; Higgins Hall offices; Split in department; math taught basically at Midtown, computer science at Westside; Feelings about Westside; enjoys the campus; Faculty in math department; hasn't grown much; about 11; 12 full; time members and always cohesive; they always got along really well; Bob Hoburg; was chairman for 19 years; knew had to organize the department; Jim Oliver; followed Hoburg as chair of the department; was a nice guy; could be intimidating to people who don't know him (especially students); Other departments; didn't really know much about other departments; Chemistry department; Dr. Paul Hines and Ron Gordano; department shattered when Gordano was killed in auto accident; WestConn presidents; came first under Bersi; left under Roach; takes special person to be able to lead a university; respected all, but didn't know any personally; Problems between faculty and administration; have been problems in the past; Steven Feldman; had problems getting along with the faculty; National events and effects on WestConn; Gulf War and his son being called; didn't pay much attention to campus because more concerned about his son; Vietnam War; was over by time he got to WestConn; taught at a community college in NY at the time; Assassinations of Robert Kennedy and Martin Luther King Jr.; WestConn atmosphere; quiet campus; "Blue collar college"; students and faculty not really involved in the university; should be a more residential college to promote university activities; Westside; Grasso Hall and plans for new dorm; plan originally to move entire university to that campus; environmental concerns also factor; not fan of two campus setup; Library; plans for renovation; build a "swing building" to house library temporarily; Parking; always been a problem since he was there; new library might consume part of the parking area; Renovations; Landscape at WestConn; likes the changes made so far at WestConn; Student Center; close to opening again; University Hall; Over head walkway; Background; grew up in Queens, NY; lived in upstate NY later; bachelor's and doctorate Albany State; Master's University of Buffalo; taught high school in upstate NY; later at Glens Falls community college; came to WestConn about 5 years after getting doctorate (side B): Final thoughts; enjoyed his time at WestConn; now teaches a high school class; time he and his wife spent in Buffalo
      - Dr. Elise Knapp (interview) Creator: Knapp, Dr. Elise Interviewer(s): Jill Polkowski and Jamie Zepko Interview location: White Hall Running time: 43 min., Apr 27, 1998; 38931; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 39)
        Coverage: 1968-1990s
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; began teaching at WestConn in 1970s and taught 27 years; taught in English department; specialized in 1700's Literature and Russian Literature; did undergrad work at Colombia University; Master's in secondary ed from WestConn; also has her Ph. D; Favorite classes to teach; Women Writers, which she introduced; Intro to Poetry; The campus in beginning; smaller; White Hall and Haas Library not there; library was on 2nd floor of Old Main; fewer administrators; one president, dean, and vice president; Newbury wasn't built; no Westside campus; Department changes; held parties; Typical student life; mostly women; mostly white (little diversity); fewer non; trad students; married students began coming in late 1970s; Dr. Janick; began to beautify campus 10; 12 years ago; Traditional classes for teachers; English department had only two Master's programs; more novels were required reading; movies and activities (less pressure in classroom); Student life on campus; more organized and simpler; fewer computers and people having an identity; Typical student; more women were motivated than men; faculty and students had more involvement; Changes in students; Dr. Haas and the role to set an example; students dressed up for class; Diversity changes; how class curriculum changed literature in classroom; Vietnam vets; non; trads in the 1980s; Vietnam War; campus protests; college not so politically active; Tuition; only $100 per semester in 1970s; raise in cost has had negative effect; Memories; bond she had w/ students and faculty; 100th Anniversary Party; terrific opportunity; good course selection; compares WestConn w/ other schools; Crime on campus; didn't exist years ago; reflective of society across the country
      - Wallace Lee (interview) Creator: Lee, Wallace Interviewer(s): Andrea Pack and Shannon Doherty Interview location: White Hall basement Running time: 35 min., Apr 1, 1998; 38930; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 42)
        Coverage: 1960s-1990s
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background at WestConn; started around 1965 and taught for 29 years; believes WestConn was still a teacher's college; Bob Holberg and Chester Floyd; other members of math department when he arrived; Math department; only 3; 4 offices for entire math department; Physical changes of WestConn; Westside wasn't here when he began; Westside; his office did move there later; taught some classes there, but also taught at Midtown; Retirement; retired about 1995; enjoyed teaching, but enjoys retirement now; spends time at War Memorial now; Background; originally from Queens, NY; graduate from John Adams high there; received bachelors degree from Teacher's College of CT (now Central CT State University); began living in CT after going to school here; Curriculum changes; got into math because he could use his mind more than hands; now math is heavily involved in computers, which is essential; graphing calculators and the benefits of using them; Computers; have made math much more easier; they have speeded the mathematical process up; have benefited math and will continue to do so; got into using them his last few years teaching; Faculty and computers; professors should start reorienting themselves to using them; Basic fundamentals of math; computers will speed up the learning; not essential to know everything; Student changes; student demonstrations on campus during Vietnam War; he took part in some demonstrations; some conflict (non; physical); Quality of student; has had both good and bad from beginning to retirement; not much difference over the years; Teaching of math; never taught any teaching of math courses; only upper level courses; Faculty participation; little activity in working conditions and salaries in beginning; what state said the faculty went along with; AAUP; was involved w/ it; was president of it on campus; went to national conventions; thought it wasn't strong enough to make changes; elite schools like Harvard, etc, were a part of it; needed a union that was less elite; AFT (American Federation of Teachers); affiliated w/ AFL; CIO; he started up chapter at WestConn and grew to be largest on campus; worked w/ Sen. William Baker; both began chapters at all 4 CSU schools; Wayne Baker; head of labor department in state; worked w/ him to get AFT set up at the CSU schools; backed by the AFL; CIO; AFT won at Western, but AAUP at the other 3; AFT President; was a former president; John Encrichrot was first (in English department); Danbury Labor Council; was president of it for 10; 11 years; Changes at WestConn after AFT; salaries went up; departments allowed to choose their department chairpersons; Animosities between administration; the administration benefited from unions; have their own as well; NEA and AFT; NEA not affiliated w/ AFL; CIO; Bob Chase, Danbury resident and president of NEA, has said want to merge w/ the AFT; such a merger would benefit teachers; which union a teacher joins depends on where they work; Governor Meskill; cut money for education while governor; Ella Grasso; was a state representative before she became governor; he met her in Washington, DC during and AFT convention there; urged her then to run for governor of CT
      - Wallace Lee and Dr. Paul Hines (interview) Creator: Lee, Wallace; and Dr. Paul Hines Interviewer(s): (no name given) Interview location: Midtown campus Running time: 15 min., Apr 6, 1994; 38929; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 43)
        Coverage: 1970s-1994
        Topics discussed: (side A) (Begins w/ Wallace Lee); Vietnam War demonstrations; something done at all colleges at time; set up committee to do so here (Committee to End the War); Andy Kahn, faculty member at time, set it up; Lee also had role on committee; they had to be careful of the radical groups (they wanted no part of them); Radical groups; many had different agendas other than ending war; some may have had communist inventions, etc.; Dr. Haas; she didn't necessarily like it, but allowed them to do so; she allowed them to have teach; ins, etc. w/ out promoting them; Student protests; eventually many students got involved; Faculty involvement; Dr. Paul Hines (head of chemistry department); Art Levy, Dan Greene, and Andy Kahn (all have moved on); Fred Farnham was a prominent student involved; was a vet involved in military service; March on Washington, DC; Farnham was involved and were others; Teach; ins; Dr. Roman was involved; Lee was as well; SGA; can't remember if they supported them financially or not (Dr. Paul Hines enters); His involvement; he was called to Dr. Haas' office everyday; she was viewed liked a grandmother looking after everybody; she thanked him for being involved and keeping things calm (Lee jumps back in); Boycott of classroom; she called him into her office asking him about his involvement; Dr. Haas and community; she worried about the students primarily (Hines); Motorcycle gang; during teach; in, they came a started yelling but nothing happened (Lee); Dr. Roman; took the opposite point of view on war (Hines); he said boo all you want, but you will listen to me (Hines); Retirement of Lee; will be retiring at end of the year; many are retiring because they fear state will take away some benefits if they don't; wasn't ready last year, but is now; has plenty to keep himself busy
      - Dr. George Linabury (interview) Creator: Linabury, Dr. George Interviewer(s): (no name given) Interview location: Office at WestConn Running time: 45 min., Apr 26, 1996; 38928; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 11, Item 44)
        Coverage: 1970s-1996
        Topics discussed: (side A): Columbia; went there after a friend advised him to go into teaching; received his Ph. D; Saudi Arabia; lived there for 7 years; Choice of WestConn; wanted to be within 60 mile radius of his father; liked the setting of the university; felt Dr. Warner and the rest of the history department were great; Change in students; improvement in terms of education; show more promise; Gulf War; talked about it in his "Linabury's Middle East Update" in his classes; felt it might eased an uncertainty students had; Male Dorms; great for progress; good for students to get away from home; feels all students should be able to live on campus; Dr. Haas; strong woman and great leader; Dr. Bersi; left too soon; Ancell School; gave tremendous burst to the college; helped in getting an International Studies program; Foreign Language requirement; believes there should be; should be provided at younger age (side B): Grad program; brought more students and more funds for books for the library; Administration; sometimes struggle, but difficulties usually come from the State; Haas Library renovation project; History department; feels it was a great department; never had any "knock; down, drag out fights"; everybody gets along; After retirement; continue teaching as an adjunct; spend more time w/ twin grandsons; travel more; Studying abroad; all students should consider doing it
      - Dr. Charles Lucas (interview) Creator: Lucas, Dr. Charles Interviewer(s): Jeffery Tarantino and Alex Barmashi Interview location: Ruth Haas Library Running time: 40 min., Apr 26, 1992; 38927; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 11, Item 45)
        Coverage: 1969-1986
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; came from Oswego, NY where he taught for 8 years; decided to come back to his home state of CT; Start at WestConn; began teaching at WestConn in 1969; they wanted someone to start experimental psychology courses; Psychology department; office located in basement of White Hall; Psych Club; student club to which he was the advisor for; Committees; graduate advisory committee, building committee for Westside; Behavior science building; the Westside building initial use; he was in charge of furniture; the architect's design of the building was to have it look native to continent, like an Aztec temple; business department moved in there later; Vietnam War; not many protests; Echo covered it; Dr. Haas; first person to interview him; her office is where Dr. Steinkrauss office is; open door policy; very pleasant woman; Growth of Psychology department; no problems; as chair, a lot of administrative problems; perhaps greatest problem was getting people to teach at night; Chair of the department; a two year title; elected by other members of department and administration; chair from 1977; 86; Size of the department; had about 7; 8 full; time faculty; offered variety of courses; never saw a decline; being in basement of White Hall has limitations; Dr. Feldman; never had any discussions w/ him; he dealt primarily w/ Dr. Steinkrauss; spent more time w/ public relations to get more money for university; used his business influence; Dr. Bersi; never had much conversations w/ him like he had w/ Dr. Haas; Psychology department improvements; the expansion of the department helped improve it; year after he was hired, the department hired two more faculty; His effect on the department and the department attraction; didn't recruit students into the department; many non; trads came into the program; Psychology of Women courses; idea came from the department itself; initially not here when he first began; Background of department; most in department upon his arrival had backgrounds in ed or child psych; his was in experimental/research psychology; Rewards of teaching; many go into graduate schools and medical schools; Library; was here when he came to WestConn; "Do; Day"; wasn't here when he got to WestConn; Dr. Janick did place the trees and shrubs around library; he wasn't involved w/ such activities; Sports; Student attitudes; most students were commuters and not on campus 24 hours per day; Events and activities; many were held in the student union; Alexander Haig; came to speak at WestConn; impressed by the amount of FBI present
      - Dr. Jane Lyman (interview) Creator: Lyman, Dr. Jane Interviewer(s): Abby Boyle and Janice Jacobs Interview location: White Hall Running time: 50 min., Apr 24, 1998; 38926; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 11, Item 46)
        Coverage: 1963-1995
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background; Smith College (Northampton, Mass); majored in music initially playing the violin; liked reading and thought about being a librarian; decided to teach; Baldwin School at Yale; taught English there and directed plays there; it was an all; women's school; enjoyed teaching; Yale Drama School; went into directing there around 1951; Yale didn't have majors, went by areas; women had been there at graduate level; she always thought of Smith as her school, not Yale; loved time there though; Swimming; did synchronized swimming at Smith; at Yale, women weren't allowed to use the gym facilities; Lord Scholar; received this honor because of her work at Yale; at one point, she was in 3 plays and directed another at same time; Happy as Larry; an Irish poetic drama she produced in her 3rd year; was awarded the money by Yale to produce it; gave it once for the faculty; Marriage; at Dwight Chapel at Yale; got married in April, graduated in June; Early years at WestConn; had taught in New Fairfield before WestConn; Dr. Haas wrote her a letter expressing interest in her; wasn't familiar w/ it at that time; began in 1963; Dr. Lovett was in charge of secondary education; she was asked to oversee the English students; English department; the communication and theater arts were are part of it then; Changes to WestConn; White Hall had been Danbury high school; college was called Danbury State College at time; library wasn't here at time, it was in Old Main; Higgins, Berkshire, and Fairfield Hall were all here; Old Main library; 3rd floor when she arrived; Close; knit community; knew each other; Picnics; Dr. Haas had picnics in Putnam Park; she always wanted the faculty w/ their families there for it; Course load; she taught five classes in beginning; since gone down to four and some think it should be three; Little control of teaching schedule; they were assigned their schedule; felt they shouldn't have 8 AM classes because it caused problems; Evening classes; Dorms; only women were allowed to stay in dorm in beginning; Spring Weekend; contests between classes; Skit Night (done by all classes and faculty) that were judged; skits were done to various things about Western life; some skits were original and others weren't; Sing Night, also done by each class; Closeness of university; these activities brought more people together; Size of school; smaller school brought more cohesiveness; Berkshire auditorium; the usual sight for the skits during Spring Weekend; Registration; was originally done in the gym; now its done by computers; the old registration process was made into a skit (side B): End of Spring Weekend; it went on for years, but it eventually just stopped; now Spring Weekend activities is different; Vietnam Era; little if anything done; all students were because they wanted to be here; because of protests, faculty told not to penalize students; Student body change; working student w/ different agendas; classes usually remained same size; Courses taught; English Composition I and II (all faculty had to teach one of them); Literature of the Stage I and II; Shakespeare (grad level); American Literature; Writing skills; all faculty in all departments should consider it important; Direction of plays at WestConn; when she arrived, she opted to teach English and not theater or direct; Fiddle on the Roof; directed by Richard Reimold; she did have a part in it, which she had to try out for; Leaning history; as a child, she was stressed memorization; Sabbatical Semester; in 1986, went to England; saw as many plays there as she could; guest speaker at Stowe School in Buckingham; Harold School; saw a play there as a guest of theirs while in England; they performed Shakespeare in way it was written; Taught English for Adolescents; those who had difficultly reading; course for teachers; Teacher's councils; Martha's Vineyard; for Princeton University Alumni College "American Writers in the Sea"; Yale Alumni Seminar; "Four American Poets"; New England Association Teacher's membership committee and liaison; CT Council Teacher's of English; conference held on WestConn campus; Children; her son is an Episcopal minister and married; her daughter is a lawyer
      - William McKee (interview) Creator: McKee, William Interviewer(s): Chris Pitman and Peter Adams Interview location: 2nd Floor of Ruth Haas Library Running time: 40 min., May 2, 1991; 38925; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 11, Item 48)
        Topics discussed: (side A ): Lab Schools (as a student); as a freshman, sent to them to observe students; as a sophomore, sent there doing things w/ students; as a junior, training period; as a senior, taught at these schools under supervising teachers; all supervisors were employed by Danbury State Teacher's College; Lab School (as principal); four lab schools were: Locust Ave, Roberts Ave, Margery Brooks, and Balmforth Ave; his job as principal was to prepare teachers; he was in charge of Locust Ave. (Fred Gamble at Roberts Ave); the superintendent of schools of Danbury later decided that the city should be in charge of these schools, not WestConn; Salary; Student teaching; more exposure to inner city schools would be beneficial; Old Main; beginning it, along w/ Fairfield Hall only buildings; hasn't changed much externally; gym, auditorium, and library were there at one point; no real labs; importance/significance of building was lost as campus grew; Changes at WestConn; all positive and can do more; like the concept of Westside providing enough students; Position in Register's office; having prior administrative experience was helpful; met w/ Dr. Cook when he was seeking position; the types of courses and how they were kept track of; Guidelines for scheduling classes; can't have conflicting classes (which didn't happen often); Transfer students; Being a "Western" person; Dr. Haas; knew her well, but worked closer w/ her deans; got along w/ her well socially; open door policy; Dr. Bersi; was on screening committee to hire replacement for Dr. Haas; Screening Committee; Dr. Bersi compared to Dr. Haas; both had open door policy, but Bersi spent less time on campus; Bersi was usually in Hartford trying to get money for the college; Gertrude Braun; she was Academic Vice President; always had high administrative position; she was dean; was an acting president for a short period between Haas and Bersi; Dean of the Night School; he held position for the undergrad level; organized the programs for undergrad; register the grad programs; primarily part; time students, but not exclusive to them; Day School Program; when he came in as student in 1940, only education taught; when he came back, more was offered; Full; time and part; time students; basically the same as both are interested in getting an education; Football team; felt they should have used the money elsewhere; football attracts students, but better use in buildings; not happy about the field house; Westside; when it was established, thought was to WestConn to Ridgefield or Wilton and turn the campus in Danbury into a 2 year college (side B): Westside (cont.); the acreage of land at Westside is huge; the amount paid for land would have been same for a little section in downtown area; Changes at WestConn; most things have been progressive; greatest increase in enrollment came in night school; Westside campus good, field house bad; White Hall good, not purchasing Locust Ave school bad; some great programs and bad ones as well; Dorms; demonstrations; the female only dorms couldn't last; Budget cuts on classroom; long term effects not major; down the line they might have effect; "Do; Day"; everyone and anyone participated in it (both faculty and students); establishing tennis courts; rebuilt parking lots; day ended w/ a festival; Dr. Janick; planting trees on campus to beautify the university